<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-12-23T16:56:36+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">MIB</title><subtitle>Up &amp; running with ML</subtitle><author><name>Semasuka Stern</name></author><entry><title type="html">Python? you mean the snake?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/12/19/python-you-mean-the-snake.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Python? you mean the snake?" /><published>2018-12-19T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-12-19T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/12/19/python-you-mean-the-snake</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/12/19/python-you-mean-the-snake.html">&lt;p&gt;No, I ain’t talking about the snake, I am talking about Python the programming language. Python is an open source high-level programming language created by Guido van Rossum and was first released to the public in 1991. Its main features are code readability by using whitespace instead of the curly braces, dynamic typing and automatic memory management. It also supports multiple programming paradigms including object-oriented, imperative, functional and procedural.&lt;!-- more --&gt; The name python comes from the fact that Rossum was influenced by “Monty Python’s Flying Circus”, a comedy series from the 1970s. he thought he needed a name that was short, unique, and slightly mysterious, so he decided to call the language Python.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/post_cont_image/fastest-prg-lang.png&quot; alt=&quot;fastest growing language&quot; /&gt;
picture credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://insights.stackoverflow.com/survey/2018&quot;&gt;stackoverflow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the time of writing this blog, Python is the fastest growing language and this trend is just starting thanks to its readability as we can read it from its core philosophy called zen of Python. You can see the entire list if you have python installed by running this command in the python interpreter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;import this
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;output
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/post_cont_image/zen-py.png&quot; alt=&quot;zen of python&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now comes the question, why is python popular in machine learning? the answer is that its syntax is easy to understand and therefore making it an awesome language for prototyping and testing during an ML project. As most of the algorithms used in Machine Learning are a bit complex, we don’t need to add another layer of complexity by worrying about a “;” that might cause the whole program not to run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another reason why Python wins is the fact that most of the ML frameworks are written in C++ with Python even though Python is not the most rapid programming language in terms of speed. To compensate for this, most of the core codes of the ML frameworks are written in C++ in order to take advantage of its speed and then wrapped with Python code for prototyping purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am hoping that now you understand why Python is the language to use when it comes to machine learning especially if you are a beginner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s install python but before we start, I have to mention one thing about Python, Python comes into two different versions Python 2 and Python 3. They are not compatible and there are some minor differences in syntax between the two. I suggest to always use version 3 since version 2 will be discontinued by 2020. I will only be using Python 3 on this blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go to the official python organization &lt;a href=&quot;https:https://www.python.org/downloads/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and download the latest version of Python for your platform (windows, mac os or Linux)and install it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/post_cont_image/py-web.png&quot; alt=&quot;python download&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NB: while you are installing Python on Windows, remember to tick the box “Add Python 3 to PATH” in order to use it in the command line&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/post_cont_image/tick-py.png&quot; alt=&quot;tick installation&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now go to your terminal/command line and type&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the installation, run the following command&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;python3
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;you should see the cursor changed to&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We gonna print the classic “hello world” on the console using the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;print&lt;/code&gt; keyword like this&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;print&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Hello world&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and this will output this&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Hello world
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;print&lt;/code&gt; keyword display anything in place in the bracket inside the “”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;you can also make some basic operation like addition&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;+&lt;/code&gt;, subtraction&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;-&lt;/code&gt;, division&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;//&lt;/code&gt;, multiplication&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;*&lt;/code&gt; and modulo&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;%&lt;/code&gt; which is the remainder of the division&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;15+2 //output: 18
&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;15-2 //output: 13
&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;15//3 //output: 5
&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;15&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;2 //output: 30
&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;15%3 //output: 0
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a brief introduction to python and an overview of its installation. I will go in depth of Python in the upcoming posts. Stay tuned by subscribing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for reading this post. If you like this post, please subscribe to stay updated with new posts and if you have a thought, I would love to hear it by commenting below.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Semasuka Stern</name></author><category term="python" /><category term="programming" /><category term="tutorial" /><summary type="html">No, I ain’t talking about the snake, I am talking about Python the programming language. Python is an open source high-level programming language created by Guido van Rossum and was first released to the public in 1991. Its main features are code readability by using whitespace instead of the curly braces, dynamic typing and automatic memory management. It also supports multiple programming paradigms including object-oriented, imperative, functional and procedural.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/assets/post_images/python-snake.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The requirements to get started in Machine Intelligence</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/12/18/what-are-the-requirements.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The requirements to get started in Machine Intelligence" /><published>2018-12-18T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-12-18T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/12/18/what-are-the-requirements</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/12/18/what-are-the-requirements.html">&lt;p&gt;Machine learning is a cross-disciplinary field that includes computer science, mathematics and sometimes domain knowledge. We can’t just focus on one part and expect to be great at it, and no you don’t have to be a master at everything to get started as it is said jack of all trades, master of none. You just need to have a basic understanding of these topics &lt;!-- more --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/post_cont_image/math-ml.png&quot; alt=&quot;math_for_ml&quot; /&gt;
picture credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://towardsdatascience.com/the-mathematics-of-machine-learning-894f046c568&quot;&gt;towardsdatascience&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s make this clear, machine learning is math so, in order to be effective and comfortable with machine learning, I will advice to start by brushing up your maths. Not all maths of course, but linear algebra, single variable and multi-variable calculus, statistics,  probability and lastly programming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we can see in the picture above linear algebra makes up 35% of ML, you need to understand what a matrice is, basic operations on matrices such as addition, subtraction, multiplication, division applied to matrices. On top of that need to know topics such as principal component analysis (PCA), singular value decomposition (SVD), eigendecomposition of a matrix, LU decomposition, QR decomposition/factorization, symmetric matrices, orthogonalization &amp;amp; orthonormalization, matrix operations, projections, Eigenvalues &amp;amp; Eigenvectors, vector spaces and norms are needed for understanding the optimization methods used for machine learning. A great course on linear algebra is the MIT linear algebra courseware found &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kjBOesZCoqc&amp;amp;index=1&amp;amp;list=PLZHQObOWTQDPD3MizzM2xVFitgF8hE_ab&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next is single variable and multivariate calculus some of the necessary topics include differential and integral calculus, partial derivatives, vector-values functions, directional gradient, hessian, Jacobian, Laplacian and lagrangian distribution. You can find a tutorial on this at Khan academy &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.khanacademy.org/math/calculus-home/multivariable-calculus&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statistic and probability are also very important since machine learning and statistics aren’t very different fields.  Some of the fundamental statistical and probability theory needed for ML are combinatorics, probability rules &amp;amp; axioms, Bayes’ theorem, random variables, variance and expectation, conditional and joint distributions, standard distributions (Bernoulli, binomial, multinomial, Uniform and Gaussian), moment generating functions, Maximum Likelihood estimation (MLE), prior and posterior, maximum a posteriori Estimation (MAP) and Sampling Methods. Check out this MIT statistic courseware &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VPZD_aij8H0&amp;amp;list=PLUl4u3cNGP60uVBMaoNERc6knT_MgPKS0&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and this Harvard probability course &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KbB0FjPg0mw&amp;amp;list=PL2SOU6wwxB0uwwH80KTQ6ht66KWxbzTIo&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;the other part of ML is programming, and as of the end of 2018, the most popular language to write machine learning is Python because it is syntactically easy to understand. Hear me right, I am NOT saying that you can only write machine learning using python, No you can write ML in Javascript, Java even Assembly language if you want to but what I mean is that python is the most suited since it has so many ML frameworks written in Python and is relatively easy to learn for beginners. Here is an awesome course on Udemy by Tim buchalka that will take you from beginner to upper intermediate level, it is worth every cent. The course is found &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.udemy.com/python-the-complete-python-developer-course/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also important to learn Data Structure and Algorithm. This is not mentioned on many resources online but I can say that this probably the most important part in programming since data structure and algorithms are the backbones of any computer science field. They are also crucial for understanding the computational efficiency and scalability of our machine learning algorithm and for exploiting sparsity in our datasets. Knowledge of data structures (Binary Trees, Hashing, Heap, Stack etc), dynamic programming, randomized &amp;amp; sublinear algorithm, graphs, gradient/stochastic descents and primal-dual methods are needed. I recommend Cracking the coding interview book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Cracking-Coding-Interview-Programming-Questions/dp/0984782850/ref=dp_ob_image_bk&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and Elements of Programming Interviews in Python &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Elements-Programming-Interviews-Python-Insiders/dp/1537713949&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of the skills are good to have but not required, these skills are data engineering which is the ability to get insight into a large amount of data using Hadoop, spark, SQL and NoSQL and data analysis and visualization skills using tableau or excel pivot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only after acquiring understanding these topics above, Do the the Andrew NG course on coursera found &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/courses?query=machine%20learning%20andrew%20ng&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.After finishing that course, you can consider specializing in any ML algorithm such as linear regression, K-means, Logistic regression, clustering, reinforcement learning etc or any ML frameworks like Tensorfow, Scikit-learn, Keras etc. I know all this list might seem daunting at first to learn all these maths and programming skills and I can’t say it will be easy because me too I am an not expert at all of them, but I can promise that if you are determined and persevere  through you can learn this and get an understanding of the foundations of ML, then it will be much much easier to debug errors (yes you are going to encounter many of those) while using complex machine learning algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last but definitely not least, you must practice! and keep on practising in order to sharpen your skills. You will understand more Machine Learning if you work on real projects. Start by using free datasets found on websites like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.data.gov/&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; or by competing at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kaggle.com&quot;&gt;Kaggle&lt;/a&gt; challenges. Another thing you can do is to read research papers found on websites like &lt;a href=&quot;https://paperswithcode.com&quot;&gt;paper with code&lt;/a&gt; to stay up to date with the latest trend in machine learning at least once a week. You should also improve your art of googling because chances are that you will run into problems or errors and you need to search on how someone else fixed it. Another area to improve is your communication skills because if you are applying for a machine learning jobs, you will likely be working in a team where you will be required to communicate and present effectively all your findings to the non-techies staffs or management board which is crucial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for reading this post. If you like this post, please subscribe to stay updated with new posts and if you have a thought, I would love to hear it by commenting below.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Semasuka Stern</name></author><category term="machine learning" /><summary type="html">Machine learning is a cross-disciplinary field that includes computer science, mathematics and sometimes domain knowledge. We can’t just focus on one part and expect to be great at it, and no you don’t have to be a master at everything to get started as it is said jack of all trades, master of none. You just need to have a basic understanding of these topics</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/assets/post_images/getting-started.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Why deep learning now?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/12/17/why-deep-learning-now.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why deep learning now?" /><published>2018-12-17T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-12-17T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/12/17/why-deep-learning-now</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/12/17/why-deep-learning-now.html">&lt;p&gt;As a refresh from my previous blog, deep learning is a subset of machine learning which learns by using layers of neurons like the ones found in our brain in order to output an expected result. The layers are organized in a way that can break down the input into different layers of abstraction. The more the layers we have, the deeper the neural network.&lt;!-- more --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/post_cont_image/nn.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;neural net&quot; /&gt;
picture credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/xanaduai/making-a-neural-network-quantum-34069e284bcf&quot;&gt;medium&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let take an oversimplified example, let’s say that this neural net above is supposed to tell which number (0-9) is a character input (the nodes in blue) while it has been trained, it has an idea on how the number 0 to 9 looks like (the node in green). So it has to simply match the input and the output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say we give it a 2. The character 2 will be divided into many small pieces of the character 2 in either straight or curved lines, These lines will be passed to the hidden layer (the orange nodes). the nodes at this layer will analyse them depending on whether these are straight or curved, they will be passed on to the next layer in the hidden section, this layer on its turn will analyse and check if there is a collection of intersections or curves between the lines from the previous layer. The more we add the layer, the more new collections are formed and that the end of the hidden layers, it can guess approximately using % which number it is because of the patterns received.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let’s answer to the pertinent question. Why has deep learning gain popularity in the recent past years? Indeed from 2010, deep learning has been massively used in the tech community as well as in other sectors. Even though this is true, artificial intelligence was not invented yesterday, nor last week. Surprisingly, it has been around since the 50’s early 60’s but from then it has evolved steadily in the ’70s. In fact, they were self-driving cars in the ’80s. Don’t believe me? watch &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_HbVWm7wdmE&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; video. Something worth mentioning is that by then AI with its sub-field was a very young academic subject and was mostly studied at the ivy league university.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/post_cont_image/usage-dp.png&quot; alt=&quot;usage_of_dp&quot; /&gt;
picture credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.ai-academy.com/six-graphs-to-understand-the-state-of-ai-academic-research-3a79cac4c9c2&quot;&gt;medium&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what happened? you may ask, well two important factors happened. processing power and data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the launch of the Intel 4004 in 1971 which was composed of 2300 transistors capable of executing between 46,250 to 92,500 instructions per second(which was groundbreaking at the time), fast forward to these days with the Intel i9 capable of performing 80 billions instructions per second which translate to a 900 times increase in processing power. this increase in the power of computers has also made computers less power hungry and very affordable to the mass population and universities which invest a lot in computers labs. Another notable mention is the Qualcomm’s Snapdragon 8cx new 7nm processor (processors found so far only in smartphones) said to be able to power a PC. if I would have been told this two years ago, I would have not believed it. This is to show you how the processing power has gone from the early days of a computer filling a whole room up to now whereas it can be carried in a pocket. But as of anything, this trend will not continue forever and we are reaching the plateau of microprocessor’s innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/post_cont_image/mlaw.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Moore_law&quot; /&gt;
picture credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moore%27s_law&quot;&gt;wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the introduction of the world wide web in 1994, the amount of data on the web, which proportionally correlated to the number of internet users (bots and humans), has skyrocketed. More people, especially from the developing countries, are discovering the internet dues to a decrease in the price of smartphones and internet bundles. There is more and more tweets, shares and clicks on the web each year. Adding to this, online retailers services, schools to hospitals need to store data from their customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/post_cont_image/web-per-min.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;use_of_internet&quot; /&gt;
picture credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.visualcapitalist.com/internet-minute-2018/&quot;&gt;visualcapitalist&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has eventually lead to the exponential creation of data, this type of data is called Big Data and is characterized by 3 Vs which are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Volume&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Velocity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Variety&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start with its volume, big data needs to be analysed with special tools like Hive, Spark or Hadoop because traditional database technologies like SQL or NoSQL won’t be able to handle its magnitude efficiently. Talking of its velocity, which is the amount of data that flows in and out a database per second. For example, a company like Facebook has to deal with a large quantity of data each second from its users who are streaming or liking a video. Finally, when it comes to the variety, we can see a rapid change in the type of data found on the internet. Contrary to the early days where we mostly found texts linked together, now we find a variety of data file format from PDF, photos, videos, audio, location data etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The perfect marriage between big data and the increased processing power has allowed the training of complex algorithms on super-computers thus leading to an increased usage of deep learning since 2010. Some interesting advancement in technology has been enabled by deep learning like changing a low-resolution image to a high definition using GANs (Generative adversarial network)(YouTube video &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HvH0b9K_Iro&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) or &lt;a href=&quot;https://lyrebird.ai/&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; website that let you create your own vocal avatar using celebrities’ voices like Trump. Another one called “everybody can dance now” (YouTube video &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WzRonX_bs34&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) uses a video from a professional dancer and apply to another video where there is a person who does not clearly dance. After the training on those two videos, the person on the second video now dances like a pro. Very cool!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can’t deny that deep learning has a bright future ahead but also we should be concerned about its drawbacks like fake news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for reading this post. If you like this post, please subscribe to stay updated with new posts and if you have a thought, I would love to hear it by commenting below.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Semasuka Stern</name></author><category term="deep learning" /><summary type="html">As a refresh from my previous blog, deep learning is a subset of machine learning which learns by using layers of neurons like the ones found in our brain in order to output an expected result. The layers are organized in a way that can break down the input into different layers of abstraction. The more the layers we have, the deeper the neural network.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/assets/post_images/why-dp-now.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">What is Machine Learning anyway? does it matter?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/12/16/what-is-machine-learning.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is Machine Learning anyway? does it matter?" /><published>2018-12-16T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-12-16T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/12/16/what-is-machine-learning</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/12/16/what-is-machine-learning.html">&lt;p&gt;Many may ask what is machine learning (ML)? we have been hearing this buzzword very often in the media or by big-name tech companies and lately, it has been used interchangeably with the word “artificial intelligence” (AI).&lt;!-- more --&gt; These days, it is very common to hear this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…the cameras on X smartphone is powered by an advanced AI that improves the image quality at night by 25.5%…”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The word machine learning/AI is overrated and used as a marketing strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going back to the title of this post, what is an Artificial intelligence and machine learning? simply put, an AI is the ability of computers to make a decision without any intervention of human (no preset rules) and exhibit a “sort” of intelligence. Machine learning, on the other hand, is a set of computer instructions (algorithms) applied on a large scale of data (a large number of bits of information) also refer as big data and train on that data to come up with predictions that might occur in the future. As more and more data is generated each day online, it has become very hard to get a sense of it using our human capacity, therefore we use a clever algorithm to understand the data and make anticipations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Machine learning can be used in different areas ranging from health, robotics to even agriculture (YouTube video &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NlpS-DhayQA&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), but as of the end of 2018, it is mostly used in the recommendation system like the one on Amazon or Alibaba that uses recent viewed/purchased item to predict the next item to buy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Machine learning is also used in the self-driving car (YouTube video &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aaOB-ErYq6Y&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) and face recognition used by Facebook and Apple on their iPhone X. This kind of machine learning uses computer vision with pattern recognition to detect an object on the picture or in the surrounding. There is another kind of machine learning called natural language processing (NLP) that rely on speech recognition to translate input using the voice. An example of the application of NLP is Siri or Google voice assistant. These kind of AI are called artificial narrow intelligence (ANI) which mean that these AI particularly excel at one single task and perform poorly in any other task which they haven’t been trained on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last but definitely not least, ML is used in the area of cyber-security and spam/malware filtering. In the first area, ML is used to detect fraud while transacting online. For example, Paypal is using ML for protection against money laundering. ML is also used to filter spam from e-mails, that’s why these days you see don’t many of those anymore in your email inbox.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These areas are the ones that come to my mind but you should not assume that the application of ML is only limited to this. Areas such as GPS navigation in order to find the shortest route, Search engine result refinement and many more are using ML.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Machine learning are grouped into two different category, supervised learning and unsupervised learning. In unsupervised ML, you dont tell the algorithm what to look for in the given dataset. this is generally used to discover pattern in data that you might not have otherwise noticed. In supervised ML, you specify what particular feature or model you want your model to learn about but comparing the input variable and the output variable in a dataset and learn the relationship between the two so it can later predict and output based on the given input.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now what is the difference between AI and Machine learning?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;the short answer is that there no big difference as to say. The long answer is that ML is a subset of Artificial intelligence. AI is considered to be more generic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/post_cont_image/ai-ml-dl.png&quot; alt=&quot;ai-ml-dl&quot; /&gt;
picture credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.nvidia.com/blog/2016/07/29/whats-difference-artificial-intelligence-machine-learning-deep-learning-ai/&quot;&gt;Nvidia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we can see in the picture above, AI is the parent and ML is its child. We can see that within ML, we also have a subset called Deep learning. Deep learning is machine learning model that mimic neurons found in our brain, to form a connected net (that’s why they are called neural network) that uses input and pass through a series of feedback within that network to produce at the end an accurate desired output. I will reserve the discussion of deep learning in another post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Machine learning models have become increasingly efficient due to two important factors. First, is the amount of data that they are fed on. As the years go by, more and more data is being generated. It has been proven that 50% of all the data from the beginning of time, were generated just within the past two years. I would like also to mention that no matter how well designed the algorithm if it is not trained with correct and clean data, the outcome will always be inaccurate. Think of the data as the fuel of the car, and the algorithm to be the car. If the car is supplied with the wrong fuel, it won’t reach far. The second factor is the improvement in terms of computing power and processor. According to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moore%27s_law&quot;&gt;Moore’s law&lt;/a&gt;, the computing capability keeps on doubling every two years, which allow us to process of a large chunk of data on advanced CPU and GPU in a fairly short amount of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, I hope now you have a basic understanding of machine learning and why it matters. At this point, I think we can’t live without Artificial intelligence because it is solving so many problems and more are yet to be solved. And yes, I know it will take so many jobs in the next decade but we can prevent this by encouraging people to switch to more creative jobs in order to remain relevant in the job market. That’s why I have created this blog, to raise awareness and to encourage people to code and start to learn Machine Learning because that’s where the world is heading, toward the 4th revolution. We have to embrace AI and also teach people from different background cultures around the world on how to utilize it for our common good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for reading this post. If you like this post, please subscribe to stay updated with new posts and if you have a thought, I would love to hear it by commenting below.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Semasuka Stern</name></author><category term="machine learning" /><category term="artificial intelligence" /><summary type="html">Many may ask what is machine learning (ML)? we have been hearing this buzzword very often in the media or by big-name tech companies and lately, it has been used interchangeably with the word “artificial intelligence” (AI).</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/assets/post_images/what-is-ml.jpg" /></entry></feed>